okay all right well good afternoon
everybody
this is Mike aalverson supervising
attorney with the disaster relief
project legal aid of North Carolina and
we're here to talk today about the
fascinating topic of property insurance
specifically with respect to natural
disasters the you know my team has been
working for over a year now on helping
people get back to the best of their
ability
after Hurricane Florence we also had in
common cases where people were impacted
by Hurricane Matthew but this would
obviously be more broadly app apply
applicable than that tornadoes lightning
other natural disasters all would fall
under the coverage of this program so as
you can see I've stolen a line from
Jerry Maguire for the title to show me
the money or not
and we'll get to that in a minute
okay why do we need insurance to quote
the comedian Chris Rock almost I have to
paraphrase because this is it this is a
family-friendly presentation in case
stuff happens nobody wants to purchase
insurance it's cost money that we would
rather put to something else we can all
understand that particularly than that
these days that you have expenses beyond
insurance but the main goal of the
insurance is to protect your investment
if you own a home that is for most
people in the country their largest
investment and if you do not have it
insured and something happens to it it's
going to be very expensive for you to
fix it and if you are doing that all out
of your own pocket that's gonna be
mostly impossible and take a very long
time if you have a mortgage property
insurance would be required under the
terms of your mortgage because the bank
is protecting is its investment
basically the collateral that is your
house so if your ass gets destroyed they
don't have anything that they can
recover from so you would have to have
it in that regard and then of course the
last point is to aid in recovery like I
say if your home was struck by lightning
and you know homeowners insurance will
help that get fixed so that you can have
a new roof and whatever else might have
been damaged in that when I say aid in
recovery it has a particular particular
with respect to disasters because the
disaster impact is so great it's one
it's not like a fender bender in your
car where you know you can get by it
with the car as is but if you have lost
your home or half of your home or what
have you
your life is turned upside down now if
you have good insurance to cover that
loss then you will it will aid in your
recovery all right so types of property
insurance two broad categories
homeowners and renters with respect to
property so homeowners insurance are
going to cover the real property that is
the house the structure and personal
property that is in the house normal
things that furniture that type of thing
and then liability meaning if if someone
is walking by your house and something
gets blown off of the house or a tree
falls from your yard and lands on
someone's car that covers you from being
personally liable for that the again
with respect to real property it is it
is the structure most insurance plan
policies works ballistically say that
they do not cover the land that is on
that the house is on you know I
mentioned the tree falling earlier the
tree would be covered the damage it will
cause but so then renter's insurance
since you're renting and you don't
actually own the structure whether it be
a condo apartment home whatever it just
covers the personal property that
possessions that are inside the home
things that are can be moved from the
home and the the next two points are our
critical points that we have certainly
with legal aid and specifically with the
disaster recovery project we have
encountered lots of issues for clients
in with respect to
these last two points on this slide
actual cash value versus replacement
cost value while those sounds similar
there's there's a big difference actual
cash value is the value of what was lost
what was damaged minus depreciation so
let's say for example your roof is
damaged and it's gonna cost $10,000 to
replace the roof but your roof was 15
years old there is a depreciation
schedule out there where the insurance
company's gonna say okay $10,000 to fix
it but it's been there for 15 years so
we're only gonna pay you $4,500 and
tying into the next deductible the next
bullet deductible that's gonna reduce
your award further so you may have
$10,000 for damage that needs to get
replaced and you get $4,500 with the
money to do it with on the other hand
replacement cost value it is just what
it sounds like if it's $10,000 to
replace your roof you're gonna get
$10,000 insurance proceeds minus the
deductible and the deductible is
basically the insurance company wants
you to have some skin in the game when
you get this recovery done or these
repairs done so the deductible is
there's several different ways that
deductibles are placed into the policy
there can be a percentage of certain
coverages under the policy it can be
just a straight number for different
types of coverages but when I say
importance of deductibles right there
what I mean is you want that deductible
to be as low as possible because that's
the money that you are going to be
responsible for so taking those last two
items into account if you have an actual
cash value policy which most residential
most homeowners policies are by the way
unless you pay for more so you like I
said earlier you get $10,000 worth of
damage and based on the depreciation
it's now 45
dollars is what you are actually going
to be compensated but you have a
deductible this $2,500 so now you have
to replace a $10,000 roof with $2,000
and that's just not possible
unfortunately I've seen many cases where
my clients have had deductibles
significantly above that and they
actually get no recovery nothing to help
fix their
all right what is covered on the real
property as I said it covers the
structure but what does that mean
exactly that means the exterior of the
dwelling or home and other structures
such as a shed a fence that might be
attached to the house those types of
things if the damage is caused by a
windstorm or hail such as during a
thunderstorm tornado or hurricane now
be so going back to the last slide in
the example the roof that's part of the
damage that would be caused by the
windstorm and should be covered by the
policy except for the depreciation and
deductible now we get to the interior of
the home and this is something that
really surprises most people when they
find out that they just because their
roof is now leaking because of the storm
the interior damage is not covered and
that's because most policies in North
Carolina include language to say that
the damage the interior is covered if
the force of the wind causes an opening
in the roof or wall and rain enters
through that opening and the insurance
companies have written these policies
this way because they're in the business
of making money and not paying on claims
so oftentimes people will have a lot of
damage on the inside but there's no
actual evident hole in the wall or roof
so their claim will be denied for that
reason and then personal property as I
mentioned earlier typical things are
home furniture electronics appliances
you know that big flat-screen TV that
you have hanging on the wall you're
gonna want that you're gonna want money
to replace that if that gets damaged but
again if the damage is not if the if
it's water damage and it's not caused by
water that came in through a hole that
the storm itself created then you're
gonna be out of luck so we're back to
the title show me the money or not
right it gave the big things that are
not covered water damage water damage
water damage every policy has a large
exclusion for water damage most people
think that they have flood insurance
when in fact they do not if you have
flood insurance your policy will say
this is a flood insurance policy and if
you don't have that it will say in big
letters this does not cover floods so if
you and if you live in a floodplain you
will have to have flood insurance if you
have a mortgage so and then flood is is
excuse me water damage is really meant
to be anything except rain anything
that's not falling from the sky so if
water presses up against this floods up
against the side of your house and leaks
in through the door that's not covered
as flood damage water dam if it if if
the river the levee breaks the quote Led
Zeppelin and here comes the flood down
the pit down the street and a big log
comes in rams through the side of your
house you're not covered because that
log was carried by the water which had
escaped its banks also doesn't include
the if you live down by the coast it
also does not include storm surge and
things of that nature that is also
excluded under these policies
alright storm came through we hunkered
down everything's it's it's all done
it's over we're not gonna die so what do
we do now well as soon as it's safe to
get in touch with your insurance agent
and say that we got hit by Hurricane
Florence freezer down shingles are lying
in the yard whatever the situation is
that takes me to that next book prevent
further damage if it is safe for you to
do so and it is practical to do so you
would want to for example tarp off a
roof that has one of those storm created
holes in it
just so that you don't have additional
damage being caused because they're
sitting and doing nothing again if
that's safe to do if if you are older or
in poor health or poor physical
condition then seek a neighbor out who
in these types of situations neighbors
will step in to help you out and
hopefully you know help tarp the roof a
little tip on tarping the roof I've seen
plenty of these where people put the
tarp halfway down one of the elevations
of the roof and that doesn't do very
much good because the water still runs
down the roof under the tarp and into
the hole so must be all the way over the
peak to prevent that and then you want
to document the damage and what I mean
here's photos photos photos everything
that was damaged in the storm or by the
storm whether it's inside the house or
outside the house you need to take
pictures lots and lots of pictures and
because we're coming up on hurricane
season June 1st now is the time to take
pictures of your house as it is today
because a picture that shows damage is
not worth as much if there's not a
picture from beforehand when there was
no damage right so take pictures of
everything
once you've got the claim filed you need
to stay in contact with your adjuster or
the agent if you do not if they lose
touch with you your claims just gonna
get tossed aside
okay now personal property if you've got
a bunch of furniture that got flooded or
rained on excuse me damaged by the storm
let's say you know the wind blew out the
window and the couch got drenched in
rain for two days because it was a big
hurricane and now that couch is a total
loss or at least you think it is you
need to document that on an inventory as
I mentioned the next one but you got to
create an inventory or a sandwich
but once that unless the insurance
company tells you you can go ahead and
throw that away you have to keep it you
cannot just throw it away because they
might come back and say well we didn't
get we didn't get a chance to look at it
oh great you got pictures but we didn't
get a chance to look at it so we're
gonna have to deny your claim on that
and you know so now you can't get a new
couch and then you should attempt to and
I know it's very very difficult after a
hurricane because everybody a lot of
people have damage and everybody's
trying to hire a contractor and/or get a
contractor and so you want to get a hold
of a contractor all caveat here
preferably a local contractor who is not
going to take your money and run without
doing any work for you because they just
came in from Texas or Louisiana or
someplace where they didn't just have a
disaster and to get that estimate you
should never have to pay for an estimate
she'll be free so what they're gonna do
is they're gonna come in they're gonna
look at everything that's damaged and
you know they're in the business of
making money so they're gonna hope they
end up getting hired by the insurance
company now what you need what they need
to do and you need to ask for is a
detailed line-by-line s2
not $5,000 for the living room and
$2,500 for the kitchen it's got to be a
line item because that's how the
insurance company is going to look at it
all right so after that after you filed
your claim insurance company is going to
do its own invest inspection and
investigation they're gonna send out
their own adjuster who may be an
employee of the company may be an
independent gesture might you know any
number of situations especially after a
natural disaster like hurricane Florence
there's gonna be a lot of people coming
in from out of town that are adjusters
that are hired just to do these claims
so after they've done their
investigation you will receive written
notice in the form of a letter that says
that you are denied coverage for any
number of reasons or you are provided
coverage and
we will pay X dollars so I guess a their
denial of coverage no money approval of
coverage some money when I say some that
goes back to our discussion from earlier
on actual cash value depreciation and
deductibles
okay so you get your letter from your
insurance agent and insurance company
and you're all excited because how okay
we're gonna get some money and it says
that you were denied oh why was there
tonight I have damage I had a policy and
I did everything they told me to do
well the policies have what are called
exclusions and as my own law professor
used to say the policy giveth and the
policy taketh away so with the policy
would say we cover for this but not this
this this this or this or not under
these circumstances like you say I had a
client today that has they have a lot of
damage on the interior of the house but
that part about the wind having to
create an opening through which that
water damage or through that would set
water gained access to the house that
excluded them from coverage then the
damage could be outside the coverage
period let's for example perhaps your
policy lapsed so your policy was a
November 1 to November 1 policy and the
storm hit on November 2 and you hadn't
paid your premium you might be in a
grace period there but you get done you
get the point
there's people have been canceled for
for various reasons and if the loss
happens outside of that one-year period
that that policy is in effect for then
you're not going to be covered
then there's prior or existing damage
what that is often referred to as
deferred maintenance that means that the
adjuster came out and looked at your
house and said well okay part of that
roof did get blown off in the storm but
from the parts that are there I can tell
that that's that is 30 years into a
20-year warranty roof so we're not
covering any of it because the shingles
should have been replaced 10 years ago
or other things like that
and there's lots of ways that can see
that they can tell if there's you know
evidence of rust or other things of that
nature that are going to tip them off
that this is
all caused by this storm or even if it
was partially it
it wasn't solely because of that and
that can also tie back into the
depreciation issue that I talked about
earlier and then the failure to comply
with policy requirements like I
mentioned before they lose track of you
it was contact with you or you don't
respond to them within the time frame
that they say that you need to respond
to that but um or and this kind of ties
back into the policy exclusions if you
had a claim for Hurricane Matthew 2016
and the insurance company paid you let's
just say 44,000 off because I have this
client and they get hit again in
hurricane Florence and the lower-middle
the same adjuster goes to the house and
let me know notices that none of the
repairs that the company had paid them
forty-four thousand dollars for in 2016
were ever made so two things happen
there they get denied on their claim for
hurricane Florence because they failed
to comply with the policy requirements
which if we pay you you fix the house as
a policy requirement and to there's a
specific exclusion for that so if you do
get money from the insurance company to
fix the house you have to fix the house
so far my client that I was just
referring to has not been the insurance
company has not demanded the money back
yet but that is a possibility
okay now I was I was approved but money
won't cover the pair okay like I talked
about at the beginning high deductibles
actual cash value and things for damage
the things were damaged were not covered
it's there are trust me there are more
ways for the insurance company to get
out of coverage than there are for you
to get into cover and that's why you
have to be very careful when you
purchase your insurance policy I
we'll tell you that the best thing to do
is to purchase the most coverage that
you can afford to cut to purchase
because though the least expensive plan
is the one that's going to have the
highest deductible it's guaranteed to
have an actual cash value policy and
there's gonna be a lot of exclusions
that you don't think about first thing
you should do now if you have a get hot
get a hold of a copy of your policy and
when they send you the three or four
pages that lists out what your coverages
are that is not your policy that's
what's called the declaration sheet or
declarations page it just tells you what
you paid for and the ventline the limits
of your life policy has nothing to do
with what the policy actually says
you'll know if you got the right policy
because it'll be about 40 pages long all
right so I've been denied or I don't
have enough money to fix my house
because of what we just talked about
what do I do
all right you can submit additional
damage information if you get a new s if
you didn't originally have an estimate
you can get an estimate and send it to
the insurance company let's say the
insurance company's estimate was ten
thousand dollars and there's you believe
there's really more damage than that
have a contractor put one together and
send it in and perhaps the insurance
company will be persuaded to give you
more money and then there's always you
can consult an attorney you can call
legal aid at the number listed at the
bottom eight six six two one nine five
two six two and see if you qualify for
our services and one of us will look
into whether that denial or the limited
amount of money that you were given was
correct under the policy or you can hire
a private attorney to do the same thing
for you
and we've reached the point where I say
do you have any questions
and let me know if we're done I'm not
seeing any questions okay
just tell me when we're done so I can